Migrating from Abator

This page details changes between MyBatis Generator (MBG) and Abator. For most users, the changes should be simple. If you extended any of Abator's classes to supply custom implementations of code generators or the Java type resolver, you will need to rework those custom classes.

The changes are listed in three categories: from required configuration changes to less common changes. Note that most changes are described assuming you are using XML configuration for MBG. If you are using Java based configuration, then the changes are still required and should be easy to deduce from the description of the XML changes.

Required for All Users

The DTD has changed. The new DOCTYPE should be

<!DOCTYPE generatorConfiguration
  PUBLIC "-//mybatis.org//DTD MyBatis Generator Configuration 1.0//EN"
  "http://mybatis.org/dtd/mybatis-generator-config_1_0.dtd">
    

The <abatorConfiguration> element is renamed to <generatorConfiguration>
The <abatorContext> element is renamed to <context>
The <daoGenerator> element is renamed to <javaClientGenerator>

Required for Many Users

MyBatis3 is now the default target runtime.
<context> element now requires an ID
The generatorSet attribute is removed from the <context> element and replaced with the targetRuntime attribute. Valid values for this attribute are MyBatis3, MyBatis3Simple, or MyBatis3DynamicSql.
The MBG classloading strategy has changed substantially, and we now recommend that you manage the runtime classpath external to MBG. If you manage the classpath with configuration entries, you must make the following changes from Abator:

Class path entries are specified at the configuration file level with the <classPathEntry> element - now a child element of <generatorConfiguration> only.
A <classPathEntry> element is not longer allowed as a child of <jdbcConnection>
The "rootClasspath" property is no longer valid for the <javaModelGenerator> element.

Rarely Required Changes

The type attribute is removed from both the <javaModelGenerator> and <sqlMapGenerator> elements. MBG has an entirely different method of supplying custom code generators than Abator. See the Extending MyBatis Generator page for full details.
The JavaTypeResolver interface has changed and is simplified. If you specified a custom implementation on the <javaTypeResolver> element, you must rework your implementation class.
The ProgressCallback interface has changed significantly. If you implemented this interface for some other execution environment, you will need to rework your implementation.

Philosophy and Apology

Some philosophical questions might be raised by this tool because the tool is more focused on database tables than on the domain model. We will take a few paragraphs to talk about this approach.

First of all, this tool does what it does. We are not making any kind of statement about how projects should, or should not, be structured. In general we are strong proponents of rich domain models - but creating a rich domain model is quite a different thing from answering the question of how that model should be persisted.

If your particular design philosophy is that the domain model drives all decisions, and that the database design is subservient to the domain model, then this tool - and MyBatis itself - may not be the proper fit for your application. In that case, we would suggest taking a serious look at Hibernate - it may fit more closely with your application design and philosophy.

But not all projects fit that paradigm. Very few truly enterprise class applications do. MyBatis can be of great help in projects where database design is seen as a co-equal to domain object design. MyBatis is not an object relational mapper, and does not attempt to transparently persist objects. So it falls on application developers to write SQL to interact with database tables.

In large or enterprise class projects, many of these factors are quite common:

Database design is often a separate function (with separate management) from OO domain design
Database designers do not have OO tools (like inheritance), so they don't think in OO terms
Application designers do not have complete control over the final form of database tables. For example, the data that seems to fit in one object for the application, may be split into several tables in the database.
The database design often ends up quite different from the OO design, leading to a significant mismatch between tables and objects.

These factors are primary indicators that MyBatis is a good candidate tool for your application, and this is the type of project where MyBatis Generator can make a significant impact. So how should MyBatis be used in this case?

The Data Access Object(DAO) pattern is still a primary pattern. MyBatis Generator can generate a basic set of objects that match each individual table. Generated code is transaction neutral. This means that it is easy to extend the generated code to add transaction attributes if more than one table is involved in a transaction. Or, you could create another DAO (or service method) that more closely matches the persistence needs of a domain object and make use of one or more generated objects in a single transaction.

As an example, consider a typical Order object - the typical header/detail problem. In some environments such an object would be persisted into at least 4 tables - two key tables, a "header" table, and a "detail" table (again, we are not making any kind of statement about whether this is "correct" design, just stating a fact). Your application should still interact with interact with the Order object, and there might be a saveOrder(Order order) method somewhere (in an OrderDAO, or a service object). That method would interact with the generated code for each of the 4 tables involved.

What has code generation bought us in this case? Several things:

Reuse - it is likely that some tables will need to be accessed from multiple different DAOs or service methods. Creating a DAO for each table promotes reuse and consistency within the application.
Database abstraction - a service layer typically defines persistence in your application. Those methods can be stabilized fairly quickly. As database design evolves:

Code can quickly be regenerated as the tables change
The service methods can be modified as necessary
Higher layers in the application remain unchanged

Developer productivity - generating table based DAOs is quick and repeatable and error free. Developers can concentrate on Object persistence, and on complex join queries if needed.
Fewer defects - because the most tedious and error prone part of any application (getting the SQL to match the objects) is automated.

MyBatis Generator Quick Start Guide

To get up and running quickly with MyBatis Generator (MBG), follow these steps:

Create and fill out a configuration file appropriately. At a minimum, you must specify:

A <jdbcConnection> element to specify how to connect to the target database
A <javaModelGenerator> element to specify target package and target project for generated Java model objects
A <sqlMapGenerator> element to specify target package and target project for generated SQL map files
(Optionally) A <javaClientGenerator> element to specify target package and target project for generated client interfaces and classes (you may omit the <javaClientGenerator> element if you don't wish to generate Java client code)
At least one database <table> element

See the XML Configuration File Reference page for an example of a configuration file.

Save the file in some convenient location (like \temp\generatorConfig.xml)
Run MBG from the command line with a command like this:

      java -jar mybatis-generator-core-x.x.x.jar -configfile \temp\generatorConfig.xml -overwrite
    

This will tell MBG to run using your configuration file. It will also tell MBG to overwrite any existing Java files with the same name. If you want to save any existing Java files, then omit the -overwrite parameter. If there is a conflict, MBG will save the newly generated file with a unique name (e.g. MyClass.java.1).

After running MBG, you will need to create or modify the standard MyBatis configuration files to make use of your newly generated code. See the Tasks After Running MyBatis Generator page for more information.

What's New in MyBatis Generator

Version 1.4.0

This is a fairly major change with these themes:

Move to Java 8
Remove support for iBatis2
General code cleanup

Breaking API Changes

Removed Plugin methods that were specific to iBatis2 (these were the clientXXXGenerated methods that accepted a TopLevelClass as a parameter).
Changed the signature of the Plugin clientGenerated method.
Removed the toXmlElement methods in the configuration classes. These methods were never properly implemented.
In the Java DOM, the Method class now requires an explicit call to setAbstract to mark the method as an abstract method. This was done to support private methods in interfaces for Java9+ code.
In the Java DOM, removed the default constructors for Method and Field
Removed several methods from CompilationUnit including isJavaInterface, isJavaEnumeration, getSuperClass, and getSuperInterfaceTypes.
Changed return types to Optionals in the DOM methods where appropriate.
Removed the getFormattedContent method from all Java and XML DOM classes. These methods are replaced by a new set of renderer classes. Note that the new renderer classes will produce code that is the same as the prior methods with very few exceptions - and those exceptions are related to bugs in the old methods.

Other Changes

Support for iBatis2 removed
Support for parsing old Ibator configuration files removed
Removed SqlMapConfigPlugin as that was specific to iBatis2
Added ability to specify a different project and package for generated model objects
Expanded the capabilities of the Java DOM and fixed a few inconsistencies

Version 1.3.7

This version contains several minor fixes and enhancements - mostly related to the MyBatis3DynamicSql runtime.

Please reference the GitHub page for milestone 1.3.7 for details. Milestone 1.3.7

Version 1.3.6

Major Enhancement

The major enhancement in this release is a new type of generated code. The generator will now create code that is based on the MyBatis Dynamic SQL library. From the first release of MyBatis Generator, the generator has created code that includes "by example" support, but that support has been limited and difficult to use. The new style of generated code supports a more natural SQL-like syntax for WHERE clauses. Additionally, WHERE clauses can be created with any combination of ANDs and ORs. This is a significant improvement to the generated code. It comes at the cost of dependency on MyBatis Dynamic SQL, and loss of compatibility with previously generated code, but we think it will be worth the change. One other benefit is that the generated code is significantly smaller and easier to understand.

Don't worry - unless you enable this change, then generator will create code exactly as it has in the past.

To enable the change, use the new "MyBatis3DynamicSQL" runtime on the <context> configuration element. To read more about using this new style of generated code, see the MyBatis Dynamic SQL Usage Notes page.

Other Announcements

After this release, support for iBatis2 code generation will be removed
After this release, the generator will require Java 8 to run. It will still generate code for earlier Java versions, but the generator itself will require Java 8.

Other Fixes/Enhancements

Please reference the GitHub page for milestone 1.3.6 for details on what else has changed in this release. Milestone 1.3.6

Version 1.3.5

Fixes/Enhancements

Please reference the GitHub page for milestone 1.3.5 for details on what has changed in this release. Milestone 1.3.5

Version 1.3.4

Announcements

In this release we have deprecated the popup menu item in the eclipse plugin for running MyBatis generator and it will be removed in the next release. The replacement is a new MyBatis generator launcher that has far more capabilities than the popup menu item.

Fixes/Enhancements

Please reference the GitHub page for milestone 1.3.4 for details on what has changed in this release. Milestone 1.3.4

Version 1.3.3

Announcements

MyBatis Generator now requires JRE 1.6 or greater

Fixes/Enhancements

Please reference the GitHub page for milestone 1.3.3 for details on what has changed in this release. Milestone 1.3.3

Version 1.3.2

Bugs Fixed

Add comments to generated constructors in the model classes so they can be merged.
Support package names with Uppercase elements.
Fixed issue #288 - Incorrect annotated countByExample method
Fixed the Maven plugin so <properties> files can be found in the project classpath.
Fixed issue #359 - make JdbcTypeInformation public
Fixed Context.toXmlElement() method to include missing attributes
Fixed CaseInsensitiveLikePlugin to add new methods to GeneratedCriteria inner class
Issue #412 - update the documentation to reflect the difference in MyBatis3 regarding generated keys.
Issue #440 - incorrect code generated for primitives with type handlers
Issue #439 - use auto boxing for primitives when appropriate
Issue #438 - keep primary key properties in database sequence
Issue #507 - RowBounds plugin generates duplicate statements
Issue #593 - CaseInsensitiveLikePlugin skipped Jdbc4 National Character Types

Enhancements

Added a new target runtime - MyBatis3Simple - that can be used to generate very simple CRUD operations on tables. This runtime produces far simpler MyBatis code than the normal MyBatis3 runtime. The produced code also has lower functionality that the normal MyBatis3 runtime. If you do not regularly use the "by example" methods, then the code produced by the MyBatis3Siple runtime may be more suitable to your project.
Added a new plugin - VirtualPrimaryKey plugin - that can be used to specify columns that act as a primary key, even if they are not defined as primary keys in the database.
Issue #328 - Added a new plugin - RowBounds plugin - that will generate an additional version of selectByExample that supports the MyBatis RowBounds function.
Created a new reference page for supplied plugins: Supplied Plugins
Issue #368 - Allowed for generation of Java Model only. If no SQLMapGenerator or JavaClientGenerator is specified in a context, then only a Java Model is generated. Also, if property "modelOnly" is set to "true" on a <table> element, then only model object and, possibly XML result maps, will be generated.
Issue #374 - Allow for specification of a file encoding for reading/writing Java files on the file system. There is a new property "javaFileEncoding" on the <context> element that can be used to specify a Java file encoding. (XML files are always read/written in UTF-8 per the spec).
Added the ability to specify custom code formatters for generated Java and XML files. See new properties on the <context> element for more information.
Added support for varargs to org.mybatis.generator.api.dom.java.Parameter class
Added support for synchronized and native to org.mybatis.generator.api.dom.java.Method class
Added support for transient and volatile to org.mybatis.generator.api.dom.java.Field class
Issue #375 - Added a new plugin - ToStringPlugin - that will generate a toString() method in the model classes. Thanks Alexei and Iwao!
Issue #233 - added GWT capability to the Serializable plugin
Issue #564 - support subpackages at the table level
Issue #590 - new plugin for <cache>. Thanks Jason Bennett!

Version 1.3.1

Bugs Fixed

Always specify <selectKey> order for MyBatis3 - position within the <insert> is not relevant.
"rootInterface" was ignored for XMLMAPPER clients
Fixed bug when a lower case class name is specified as a domain object name
Fixed issue #174 - incorrect format of order by clause in selectByExampleWithBlobs

Enhancements

Added a new MyBatis3 generator that generates code based solely on annotations with no generated XML. Configuration settings for this new generator are as follows:

The targetRuntime attribute of <context> element is MyBatis3
The type attribute of <javaClientGenerator> element is ANNOTATEDMAPPER

Added a new MyBatis3 generator that generates code based on a mix of annotations and generated XML. Configuration settings for this new generator are as follows:

The targetRuntime attribute of <context> element is MyBatis3
The type attribute of <javaClientGenerator> element is MIXEDMAPPER

Add support for JDBC types NCHAR, NCLOB, NVARCHAR to match MyBatis3.
Added support for "useGeneratedKeys" in MyBatis3. See <generatedKey> for details.
Added support for immutable objects and constructor based result maps in MyBatis3. See <table> and/or <javaModelGenerator> for details.
Added support for initialization blocks in the Java DOM
Issue #214 - Added the ability to supress all comments in generated code. See <commentGenerator> for details.

Version 1.3.0

Moved to mybatis.org, renamed MyBatis Generator
MyBatis generator will continue to support XML configuration files from Ibator. However, any new features will only be implemented in MyBatis formatted configuration files. Some minimal changes are required to migrate Ibator formatted configuration files to the new DTD for MyBatis Generator.
Configuration settings for MyBatis 3 are as follows:

The targetRuntime attribute of <context> element must be changed to MyBatis3
The type attribute of <javaClientGenerator> element must be changed to XMLMAPPER

Removed support for suppressTypeWarnings property in the <context> element. This confusing property has become unmanagable due to confusion between @SuppressWarnings("unchecked") and @SuppressWarnings("rawtypes") in the different compilers. This was only used in the corner case where code generated with Ibatis2Java2 targetRuntime was to be compiled with a JSE 5.0 compiler.

Version 1.2.2 (Never Released)

Announcements

The org.apache.ibatis.ibator.api.CommentGenerator interface has changed. Classes that implement this interface must be changed. With this change, implementing classes have access to many more data elements from which to generate comments. Additionally, this change makes the comment generator interface more consistent with the other public Ibator interfaces. Details of the change follow:

Methods which accepted the parameter FullyQualifiedTable now accept the parameter IntrospectedTable instead. The FullyQualifiedTable instance is available through the method IntrospectedTable.getFullyQualifiedTable().
Methods which accepted the String parameter columnName now accept the parameter IntrospectedColumn instead. The column name is available through the method IntrospectedColumn.getActualColumnName().

Important Note: any implementation that subclasses the Ibator supplied class DefaultCommentGenerator does not need to change immediately with this release. The old methods have been deprecated and will be removed with the next release of Ibator - so subclasses should be reworked as soon as convenient.

The SQL Map generator has changed in that it no longer prepends the string "ibatorgenerated_" to every generated XML id. If you were relying on these generated names in other code, you can force Ibator to prepend the string with the property useLegacyXMLIds on the <SqlMapGenerator> configuration.
Ibator is now built with Maven and includes a Maven plugin

Bugs Fixed

NPE when no DAOs are generated.
IBATIS-579 - Don't allow column names that contain spaces to break across lines in generated XML.
Fixed NPE and incorrect calculation in generated equals method (from EqualsHashCodePlugin) when certain fields are null - thanks to Benjamin Klatt for finding this bug.
IBATIS-601 - improper validation of <generatedKey>
IBATIS-609 - incorrect parsing of Java generic types
Fixed spelling error LONCVARCHAR to LONGVARCHAR (thanks Allard)
Fixed IBATIS-731 - change name of primary key variable to avoid conflicts
Fixed IBATIS-699 - Overwrite unmergeable XML files if enabled
Fixed issue where insertSelective failed if there is a sequence generating the primary key (issue only with iBATIS3)

Enhancements

IBATIS-569 - Modified the IbatorRules implementation to make it easier for plugins to provide custom implementations of IbatorRules. See the Javadoc for the new class org.apache.ibatis.ibator.internal.rules.IbatorRulesDelegate for more information.
IBATIS-571 - Added support for automatically delimiting SQL keywords if they are used as column names in tables. See the <ibatorContext> page for more information.
IBATIS-577 - Define SQL fragments for column lists to improve reusability of generated code. Thanks to Iwao AVE! for the idea and the initial patch.
Added new -verbose command line argument. See the Running Ibator page for more information.
Added logging statements for use in debug. See the Logging page for more information.
Added new example plugin to demonstrate adding case insensitive LIKE support to generated Example classes. See the <ibatorPlugin> page for more information.
Added "delimitAllColumns" attribute to table configurations. This supports databases like PosgreSQL that are case sensitive for identifiers. See the <table> page for more information.
Added a page explaining how to deal with case sensitivity in PostgreSQL. See the PostgreSQL page for more information.
IBATIS-586 - Added the ability to specify nested property elements on columnOverrides. See the <columnOverride> page for more information. Thanks to Dan Turkenkopf for the idea and a nice initial patch.
The IntrospectedColumn class now contains any column remarks returned during database introspection. This may be useful for some CommentGenerators.
IBATIS-592 - Added attributes to IntrospectedTable that contain the calculated SqlMap namespace, and the calculated runtime table names. These can now be overridden in plugins.
Fixed addCriterionfor JDBC* methods so that they all do a null check.
Fixed IbatorRunner so that configuration errors are shown (thanks to Karel Rank)
IBATIS-605 - Added Informix Dialect for <generatedKey>
Addedd support for "distinct" on select by example methods
Added new "or" method to example classes
Added new "useCompoundPropertyNames" property on <table>
Enabled a far simpler method for extending the example classes
EqualsHashCodePlugin now generates far superior methods

Version 1.2.1

Bugs Fixed

Fixed the IbatorObjectFactory so it will find internal classes from the context classloader.
Fixed IBATIS-565 - ill formed comment in the SqlMapConfigPlugin

Enhancements

Modified plugin methods for model fields, getters, and setters so that the plugin will know which type of class (Primary Key, Base Record, or Record with BLOBs) is being generated.
Added methods to IntrospectedTable to get/set attributes. This allows plugin classes to maintain table based state between plugin calls.
Added initialized method to the plugin API. This allows plugins to alter some of the fundamental code generation items (like the name of a generated class, for example).
Added an example plugin to show usage of the initialized method.

Version 1.2.0

Announcements

With version 1.2, Abator is renamed to Apache iBATIS Ibator. Several changes have been made to the XML configuration as well as the Java API. See the Migrating from Abator page for detailed information about changes needed to existing Abator configuration files.

Bugs Fixed

Fixed the JavaTypeResolver so that columns with unsupported data types may be overridden by configuration.
Fixed IBATIS-523 - a bug in the pre-release version of the EqualsHashCodePlugin
Fixed IBATIS-542 - upgrade the build to Ant version 1.7.1

Enhancements

Ibator now includes a plugin mechanism. This mechanism can be used to add to or modify the code generated by Ibator. If you have previously extended one of Abator's code generators to change their behavior, we strongly suggest that you move to a plugin. See the <ibatorPlugin> page for detailed information.
Ibator ships with the following plugins:

A plugin that will generate an SQL Map Config File (org.apache.ibatis.ibator.plugins.SqlMapConfigPlugin)
A plugin that will make generated model classes Serializable (org.apache.ibatis.ibator.plugins.SerializablePlugin)
A plugin that will add equals and hashCode methods to generated model classes (org.apache.ibatis.ibator.plugins.EqualsHashCodePlugin)

Added support for "runtimeCatalog" and "runtimeSchema" properties to the <table> configuration element. Thanks to Dan Turkenkopf for the idea and the patch!
New generated method - insertSelective. This method will allow you to use column defaults on a table definition on insert
Added the ability to specify a that DAO implementation classes be in a separate package from the DAO interface classes.

Changes from Abator

There are several breaking changes between Ibator and Abator. This list details the changes, and has methods of resolving the differences.

JSE 5.0 or higher is required for Ibator
Ibator does not contain the "legacy" code generators from Abator. You must choose "Ibatis2Java2" or "Ibatis2Java5" as a target runtime - and code generated from Ibator is compatible with iBATIS version 2.2.0 or higher only. If you are using an earlier version of iBATIS - upgrade! If you are not able to upgrade, then you must continue to use Abator.
The classloading strategy in Ibator is changed from Abator. In all cases, we now recommend specifying the classpath external to Ibator and we further recommend that you do not use the <classPathEntry> element. You may specify classpath entries if you feel you must, but those entries will only be used when loading JDBC drivers of Java model root classes. If you write a custom extension to Ibator, or a plugin, you must specify that classpath entry external to Ibator.
The API for extending Ibator is significantly changed from Abator. In most cases, implementations of the old Abator interfaces should be converted to Ibator plugins. See the Extending Ibator for more information.
The afterXXXGenerationHook methods have been removed from all Ibator supplied implementations of the core interfaces. If you were extending an Ibator supplied implementation to make use of these methods, then you must migrate your code to an Ibator plugin.
The build has been significantly modified and now includes an Emma based code coverage report.
Changes to the XML configuration file are required. See the Migrating from Abator page for detailed information

Version 1.1.0

Announcements

The next release of Abator will require JRE 5.0 or higher.
Java2 is now the default generator set. This will cause different code to be generated if you have not specified a generator set previously. To remedy this, set the generator set to "Legacy".

New Generated Methods

Abator will generate these new methods:

countByExample
This method will return an integer representing the number of rows in a table that match the given criteria.
updateByExample
This method will update all rows in a table that match a given criteria. This method is available in the Java2 and Java5 generator sets only. There is also a "selective" version of the method that only updates certain columns of a table (the selective version of this method is probably the more useful version to use in most situations).

Bugs Fixed

Fixed bug for corner case where a criteria class is created, but no criteria are set.
Fixed a bug that caused the JavaModelGenerator's "trimStrings" property to fail
Fixed the XML file merger so that internal entities are preserved
Fixed the XML configuration parser so that external entities are handled properly
Fixed bug - incorrect datatype mapping for JDBC BIT datatype
Fixed bug where Abator generated incorrect properties for certain database columns (for example, if the column name is I_NAME)

Miscellaneous Changes

Added the ability to specify properties to ignore qualifiers and change runtime table names in the generated SQL for a table. Primary use cases for this support include:

Generating objects for a table that has a public synonym or alias
Generating objects for a table that exists in many schemas, and the schema will be selected at runtime

See the <table> reference page for more information, or the Oracle reference page for an example.
Added support for delimiting SQL identifiers for the use cases where identifiers contain spaces or SQL reserved words. See the <table>, <abatorContext>, and <columnOverride> reference pages for more information.
Added SYBASE dialect for generated keys. See the <generatedKey> reference page for more information.
Added DB2_MF (DB2 on Main Frames) dialect for generated keys. See the <generatedKey> reference page for more information.
Abator will now automatically escape identifiers that contain the $ or # characters as these characters have special meaning in iBATIS configuration files.
Added a clear method to the generated example classes (in the Java2 and Java5 generator sets only). This allows reuse of these classes.
Added the ability to specify that result maps should use column indexes rather than column names in the result mappings. Primary use cases for this support include:

When tables have columns whose name is only differentiated by case (e.g. "first name" and "First Name")
When you want to make the selects as fast as possible (there is a slight performance benefit when using column indexes)

See the <table> reference page for more information.
Made the generated Example and Criteria classes extendable. Added some documentation about how to extend these classes. See the Extending the Example Classes reference page for more information.
Made the legacy DAOs extendable.
Added the ability to provide a renaming rule for columns. This is for the use case where columns have a common prefix that should be removed before calculating the property name. See the <columnRenamingRule> reference page for more information.
Added support for persisting a configuration to XML - this to enable a graphical editor in the future.
Add afterXXXGenerationHook() methods in all generators to enable adding extra Java code or XML elements to any generated object. This will make it easier to create customized generators.
API change to allow generating with selected contexts rather than the entire config file.
API change to allow generating with selected tables rather than the entire config file.
Exposed new support for selecting tables and/or contexts to the command line and the Ant task - this has added an advanced syntax to the command line for Abator. See the Running Abator reference page for more information.
rootClass and rootInterface may now be specified for each table. See the <table> reference page for more information.
If a rootClass is specified for any table, Abator will now check in the rootClass to see if a generated property already exists in the root class. If it does, Abator will not generate the property. The <javaModelGenerator> element now accepts a property to specify the classpath of the rootClass. See the <javaModelGenerator> reference page for more information. Thanks to Ashok Madhavan for the beginnings of this code.
Allowed specifying a type (pre or post) for the generated key element. See the <generatedKey> reference page for more information.
Added a comment generator interface to enable generation of custom comments. See the <commentGenerator> reference page for more information.

Version 1.0.0

Generator Sets

A generator set is a set of code generators (SQL Map Generator, Java Model Generator, DAO Generator, and Java Type Resolver). Abator now ships three different generator sets. The generated code from these three generator sets is slightly different, and the use of the generated objects is slightly different too. The concepts are exactly the same. With the newer generator sets, the "by example" methods have been vastly improved. It is now possible to generate virtually any WHERE clause (including IN and BETWEEN predicates). Lastly, the new generator sets generate much more concise code - the DAOs and SQL Maps are of normal size, and there are no extraneous methods. The example class in the new generator sets encapsulates all the function needed to generate dynamic queries.

The three generator sets shipped with Abator are as follows:

Legacy
This generator set generates code that is the same as previous versions of Abator. There are some limitations with this generator set and we strongly recommend that you choose one of the other sets. However, this set remains the default for now. This generator set will likely be removed in a future version of Abator.
Java2
This generator set generates code that is compatible with iBATIS versions 2.2.0 and higher. With this generator set the "by example" methods are much more powerful than in the legacy set. It is now possible to generate virtually unlimited SQL WHERE clauses with Abator generated code (including "IN" and "BETWEEN" clauses). This generator set will likely become the default set in a future version of Abator.
Java5
This generator set has the same capabilities as the Java2 generator set with the added feature of generating code that is JSE 5.0 compliant using parameterized types and annotations.

Important: code generated with the Java2 or Java5 generator sets is not 100% compatible with code generated with the Legacy set - especially in the use of the "by example" methods. Also note that the "by example" methods in these generator sets rely on iBATIS dynamic SQL support that is missing in iBATIS versions prior to version 2.2.0.

A generator set is selected with the generatorSet attribute of the <abatorContext> element. See the <abatorContext> reference page for more information.

Use of the example classes is different with the different generator sets. See the Example Class Usage page for more information.

Model Types

A model type is used to give you more control over the types of domain objects generated by Abator. Abator now supports three different types of domain models as follows:

conditional
This model is similar to the hierarchical model except that a separate class will not be generated if that separate class would only contain one field. So if a table has only one primary key field, that field will be merged into the base record class. This model type is the default. Note that this model type may generate classes that are not 100% with classes generated in previous versions of Abator.
flat
This model generates only one domain class for any table. The class will hold all fields in the table.
hierarchical
This model is the same as the model shipped with the initial versions of Abator. This model will generate a primary key class if the table has a primary key, another class that holds any BLOB columns in the table, and another class that holds the remaining fields. There is an appropriate inheritance relationship between the classes.

Model types can be specified as a default for an entire context, and you may override the default for each table in a context. See the <abatorContext> reference page for more information about setting the context default.. See the <table> reference page for more information about setting a model type for specific tables.

Important: the default value is conditional - this is a non-backward compatible change from previous versions of Abator.

updateByPrimaryKeySelective

This is a new mapped SQL statement, and new DAO method, that will only update columns whose corresponding properties in the parameter class are non-null. This can be used to update certain columns in a record without needing to update the entire record.

Important: any column that is mapped to a primitive type will always be updated.

Miscellaneous Changes

Added the ability to specify a table alias. This aids in reuse of generated SQL map elements. See the <table> reference page for more information.
Fixed the XML file merger so that extraneous blank lines at the end of the file are removed.
Added the ability to specify a type handler for table columns. See the <columnOverride> reference page for more information.
Added the ability to specify the visibility of the DAO "by example" methods. This allows you to make the methods private for internal use only. See the <javaClientGenerator> reference page for more information.
Added the ability to override the naming convention for DAO method names. See the <javaClientGenerator> reference page for more information.
Added the ability to specify wildcards for schema or tableName in a table configuration. This will allow generation of many tables with a simple XML configuration. See the <table> reference page for more information.
Added the ability to escape wildcard characters in schema or table names if required by the driver. See the <table> reference page for more information.
Added the ability to suppress JSE 5.0 type warning messages for non-parameterized types if you are using the Legacy or Java2 generator sets in a JSE 5.0 environment. See the <abatorContext> reference page for more information.
Added the ability to specify an external properties file for passing parameters into an Abator configuration file (like the iBATIS properties file). See the <properties> reference page for more information.
The Ant task now supports a "verbose" attribute. See the Running Abator page for more information.
The Ant task now supports a nested property set for passing values into an Abator configuration file. See the Running Abator page for more information.

Introduction to MyBatis Generator

MyBatis Generator (MBG) is a code generator for MyBatis MyBatis. It will generate code for all versions of MyBatis. It will introspect a database table (or many tables) and will generate artifacts that can be used to access the table(s). This lessens the initial nuisance of setting up objects and configuration files to interact with database tables. MBG seeks to make a major impact on the large percentage of database operations that are simple CRUD (Create, Retrieve, Update, Delete). You will still need to hand code SQL and objects for join queries, or stored procedures.

MBG generates code in different styles, and for different languages, depending on how it is configured. For example, MBG can generate Java or Kotlin code. And MBG can generate MyBatis3 compatible XML - althought that is now considered a legacy use of MBG. The newer styles of generated code do not require XML.

Depending on how it is configured, MyBatis Generator may generate:

Java or Kotlin classes that match the table structure. This may include:

a class to match the primary key of the table (if there is a primary key)
a class to match the non-primary key fields of the table (except BLOB fields)
a class to include the BLOB fields of a table (if the table has BLOB fields)
a class to enable dynamic selects, updates, and deletes

There is an inheritance relationship between these classes as appropriate. Note that the generator may be configured to generate different types of POJO hierarchies - for example, you may choose to generate a single domain object for each table if you so desire.

In some cases, MBG will generate MyBatis3 Compatible SQL Map XML Files. MBG generates SQL for simple CRUD functions on each table in a configuration. The generated SQL statements include:

insert
update by primary key
update by example (using a dynamic where clause)
delete by primary key
delete by example (using a dynamic where clause)
select by primary key
select by example (using a dynamic where clause)
count by example

There are different variations of these statements depending on the structure of the table (for example, if the table doesn't have a primary key, then MBG will not generate an update by primary key function).

Java or Kotlin client classes, interfaces, and Kotlin extension methods that make appropriate use of the above objects. The generation of client classes is optional. MBG will generate a mapper interface that works with the MyBatis 3.x mapper infrastructure

MyBatis generator is designed to run well in an iterative development environment, and can be included as an Ant task, or a Maven plugin, in a continuous build environment. Important things to note when running MBG iteratively include:

MBG will automatically merge XML files if there is an existing file with the same name as the newly generated XML file. MBG will not overwrite any custom changes you make to the XML files it generates. You can run it over and over again without fear of losing custom changes to you XML. MBG will replace any XML elements that were generated in a previous run.
MBG will not merge Java files, it can either overwrite existing files or save newly generated files with a different unique name. If you make changes to the generated Java files and run MBG iteratively you will have to merge the changes by hand. When run as an Eclipse plugin, then MBG can automatically merge Java files.
MBG will not merge Kotlin files, it can either overwrite existing files or save newly generated files with a different unique name. If you make changes to the generated Kotlin files and run MBG iteratively you will have to merge the changes by hand.

Running with Eclipse

When running as an Eclipse feature the generator can also merge Java files and save user modifications to the generated Java files. The generator uses the Eclipse Java parser and AST walker to accomplish this. The Eclipse feature also has a few user interface enhancements that make the generator somewhat easier to run. Lastly, the Eclipse feature contributes a full user manual for the generator to the Eclipse help system.

The Eclipse feature can be found on the Eclipse marketplace here: https://marketplace.eclipse.org/content/mybatis-generator.

Dependencies

MBG has no dependencies beyond the JRE. Java 8 or above is required. Also, a JDBC driver that implements the DatabaseMetaData interface, especially the getColumns and getPrimaryKeys methods is required.

Generated Code Dependencies

MBG will generate code in different styles. This is controlled by the "targetRuntime" attribute of a <context> element. All runtimes generate code that is dependent on MyBatis. Some of the runtimes generate code that is also dependent on MyBatis Dynamic SQL. The following table shows the required dependencies in the generated code.

Runtime | MyBatis Generator Version | MyBatis Version | MyBatis Dynamic SQL Version
MyBatis3, MyBatis3Simple | Any | 3.0+ | N/A
MyBatis3DynamicSQL | 1.3.6 - 1.3.7 | 3.4.2+ | 1.1.0 - 1.2.1
MyBatis3DynamicSQL, MyBatis3Kotlin | 1.4.0 | 3.4.2+ | 1.1.3+
MyBatis3DynamicSQL | 1.4.1+ | 3.4.2+ | 1.3.1+
MyBatis3Kotlin | 1.4.1+ | 3.4.2+ | 1.4.0+

Support

Support for MyBatis Generator is provided through the MyBatis user mailing list. You may subscribe to or view the mailing list through Google code here:

http://groups.google.com/group/mybatis-user

If you think you have found a bug, please ask a question about it on the user list first, before creating a new ticket. If you find a bug, or have a new feature request, you may open a new issue at GitHub here:

https://github.com/mybatis/generator/issues